Werner Seligmann Papers
Werner Seligmann Papers
- Project records
  - CORTLANES BOWLING CENTER 391 State Rd. 13, Cortland, New York (1961) [Recreational]
    Bowling center and bar. Sponsor/client: Cortlanes. Collaborators/partners: Drawings by "HC."
    - Drawings, 1961; preliminary and partial working drawings (Tube 29)
    - Drawings, undated; perspectives, elevations, plans, exterior and interior (Box 30)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, perspectives, plans, construction and reconstruction; 5 (Box S-2)
  - CULTURAL ARTS PAVILION PROJECT DESIGN, COMPETITION Newport News, Virginia (1984) (not built) [Cultural]
    Major competition. Sponsor/client: City of Newport News; National Endowment for the Arts Design, Arts Design Program.
    - Drawings, undated; site plan, elevations, sections, perspectives, sketches (Tube 30)
    - Presentation board 86, site plan, plans, perspectives
    - Presentation board 87, plan, section, perspective
    - Project material, 1984; correspondence, competition materials (Box 95, Folder 68)
    - Slides, site plans, elevations; 5 (Box S-2)
  - CULTURAL CENTER, COMPETITION* Singen, Germany (undated) (not built) [Cultural], town civic center
    - Slides, models, earlier existing structures; 5 (Box S-2)
  - DATES CHEVROLET COMPANY Groton, New York (not built) [Commercial], automobile showroom and service center
    - Drawings, undated; elevations, plan (Box 42)
    - Drawings, 1961; working drawings (Tube 31)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
    - Slides, elevations, plans; 2 (Box S-2)
  - EAST SYRACUSE LIBRARY (ESL) East Syracuse, New York (undated) (not built) [Cultural]
    - Drawings, 1968; sketches, preliminary studies and presentation drawings (Tube 32)
    - Drawings, undated; plans, sketches (Box 95, Folder 39)
    - Model, restored; approximate dimensions: 16.5"L 12"W x3.5"H (Box Model-2)
    - Slides, plans; 2 (Box S-2)
  - ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, COMPETITION* Obstalden, Switzerland (undated) (not built) [Educational]
    - Drawings, undated; plans and section (Box 95, Folder 84)
  - ELLIS FIELD REDEVELOPMENT (EFR) 500 McKool Ave., East Syracuse, New York (1970) [Recreational]
    Project for playing fields, locker rooms, swimming pool with air-inflated dome. Sponsor/client: Village of East Syracuse, New York. Collaborators/partners: Mechanical: Flack & Kurtz (NYC); Photographer: Charles C. White.
    - Drawings, 1969-1970; phase I and II working drawings, presentation drawings, sketches (Tube 33)
    - Project material, 1965-1970; site plan, sections, axonometrics, plans, model, completed project; specifications on microfilm (Box 40)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
    - Slides, site plans, axonometrics, elevations, sections, plans, models, general views; 35 (Box S-2)
  - ELM-MAPLE HOUSING, See ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - ELM ST. Ithaca, New York; ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - MAPLE AVE. Ithaca, New York.
  - ENRICO FERMI MEMORIAL PAVILION, COMPETITION Chicago, Illinois (1957) (not built) [Cultural]
    - Project material, 1957; sections, elevations, plans; competition materials (Box 12)
    - Slides, sections; 6 (Box S-2)
  - FELIX NUSSBAUM HOUSE, COMPETITION Osnabrueck, Germany (1995) (not built) [Cultural]
    (Alternate names: Nussbaum Museum)
    International competition for museum to house the paintings of artist Felix Nussbaum. Sponsor/client: City of Osnabruck. Collaborators/partners: Associated Architect: Mark Shapiro.
    - Drawings, undated; base maps and drawings, presentation drawings (Tube 34)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 35)
    - Drawings, student re-drawings (Tube 176)
    - Model, restored; approximate dimensions: 27"L x 18"W x 8"H (Box Model-5)
    - Presentation board 8, site plan, "1193."
    - Presentation board 9, site plan, plans, "Plan-Niveau" "1193."
    - Presentation board 10, "Schnitt," "Ansicht lotter strasse," Ansicht Heger-Tor-Wall," Ansicht Hagenpattweg," "1193."
    - Presentation board 11, "Schnitt," "Getrennte Nutzung Nach Offnungszeiten," Erschliessungen," "Schema Der Luftfuhrung," Beziehung Zur Altstadt Und Heger Tor," Beziehung Zu Villa Schlicker Und Museum," "Polaritat: eh. Baune Haus (villa Schliker) Und Felix Nussbaum - Haus," "Beziehung Nussbaum - Hain, Garten Der Stille Umd Nussbaum Haus," "1193."
    - Project material, 1995-1996; perspective, working details, elevation, section, model; correspondence and competition materials (in German), article (Box 6)
    - Slides, maps, analytical and explanatory drawings, site plans, elevations, drawings and sketches, perspectives, sections, plans, models, earlier existing structures, art work, competition entries by other architects; 150 (Box S-2)
  - FIORENTINO'S JEWELRY SHOP REMODELING Cortland, New York (not built) [Commercial]
    - Drawings, 1963; sketches (Tube 36)
  - FIRST CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH REMODELING (CoCR) Cortland, New York (1965) [Religious]
    Remodeling of existing church. Sponsor/client: First Congregational Church. Collaborators/partners: Drawings by "TAZ' and "RFF."
    - Drawings, 1964-1965; preliminary and working drawings (Tube 37)
    - Slides, earlier existing structures; 1 (Box S-2)
  - FOWLER'S DEPARTMENT STORE ENTRY*, Binghamton, New York (not built) [Commercial]
    Urban design proposal. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA).
    - Slides, model; 50 (Box S-2)
  - FRANKLIN SCHOOL PRE-KINDERGARTEN RENOVATION 262 Conklin Ave., Binghamton, New York (1973) [Educational]
    (Alternate names: Benjamin Franklin Elementary School)
    Interior renovations. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Board of Education. Collaborators/partners: Architect: Eugene Beautz (Binghamton); Consulting Engineers: Frank L. Jennings.
    - Drawings, 1973; working drawings (Tube 38)
    - Drawings, undated; plan, axonometric (Box 20)
    - Slides, general and interior views; 25 (Box S-2)
  - FT. LAUDERDALE RIVERFRONT PLAZA DESIGN, COMPETITION Ft. Lauderdale, Florida (1983) (not built) [Government]
    Competition for new plaza along intracoastal waterway. Sponsor/client: Downtown Development Authority of Ft. Lauderdale.
    - Drawings, 1982; base and presentation drawings, sketches (Tube 39)
    - Drawings, student re-drawings (Tube 176)
    - Project material, undated; plans, axonometrics, perspectives, gridlines; competition materials (Box 11)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
    - Slides, axonometrics, elevations, referential images, site map, design sketches and studies, analytical and explanatory diagrams, perspectives, sections, plans, earlier existing structures, competition entries by other architects; 100 (Box S-2)
  - HERITAGE PARK Elmira, New York (not built) [Government]
    This project was an urban design study of circulation, parking, planting, and potential development. Sponsor/client: City of Elmira.
    - Drawings, 1966-1969; studies (Tube 40)
    - Slides, site plans, model; 10 (Box S-2)
  - HIGGINS SUMMER RESIDENCE Skaneateles, New York (1955) [Residential], small summer house
    - Project material, 1954-1955; elevation, perspective, plan, exterior (Box 95, Folder 56)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, perspectives, sections, plans, general views; 15 (Box S-2)
  - HIGH SCHOOL, RAMIBUHL, COMPETITION* Zurich, Switzerland (undated) (not built) [Educational]
    This project was a large high school in Switzerland. Collaborators/partners: Photographer: Peter Grunert (Switzerland).
    - Project material, undated; photo of model (Box 95, Folder 85)
  - HOMER AVENUE NO. 13*, Cortland, New York (not built) [Residential], proposal for minor renovations
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 41)
  - HOMER AVENUE NOS. 9-11, See SELIGMANN OFFICE AND RESIDENCE REMODELING, Cortland, New York.
  - HOUSE SCHEME 1* (not built) [Residential]
    - Presentation board 88, plot plan, elevations, sections, perspective
    - Slides, perspective, plan, elevation, section; 1 (Box S-2)
  - HOUSE SCHEME 2* (not built) [Residential]
    - Presentation board 89, plot plan, plan, elevations, section
  - HUNTINGTON CAMP DORMITORY (HUCADO) Raquette Lake, New York (1969) [Educational]
    (Alternate names: Camp Huntington)
    Dormitory for summer camp. Sponsor/client: NYS University Construction Fund. Collaborators/partners: Mechanical: Galson & Galson Consulting Engineers, Inc. (East Syracuse).
    - Drawings, 1968; working drawings (Tube 42)
    - Presentation board 58, Elevations
    - Project material, undated; site plans, elevations, axonometrics, model, exterior and site; sketch; award submission; text (Box 54)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1969), site plans, axonometrics, elevations, plans, construction and reconstruction, models, earlier existing structures, exterior and interior details, general views; 35 (Box S-2)
  - IBBOTSON BUILDING REMODELING (IBR) Homer, New York (not built) [Commercial], minor interior remodeling
    - Drawings, 1963-1964; working drawings (Tube 43)
  - IBBOTSON RESIDENCE REMODELING Homer, New York (not built) [Residential], minor interior remodeling
    - Project material, undated; sections, plan (Box 95, Folder 43)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
  - INTERFAITH CHAPEL* Cortland, New York (not built) [Religious]
    - Project material, undated; plans, elevations, perspectives on original presentation [Newspaper box] (Box 91)
    - Slides, models, perspectives; 10 (Box S-2)
  - ITA Ithaca?, New York (not built) [Residential]
    - Drawings, 1964; site and floor plans, section (Tube 44)
  - ITHACA COMMONS CENTER (ICC) 171 East State St., Ithaca, New York (1982) [Mixed Use]
    (Alternate names: Center Ithaca)
    Urban infill project with retail, commercial, and residential components. Sponsor/client: Ithaca Center Associates; I. Stanley Goldberg; Developer: D.M. Abbott Investors Corp. Collaborators/partners: Architects: WSA, Joel Bostick, Peter Guzy; Associate Architects: Perry, Dean, Stahl & Rogers (Boston); Structural: Bolton & Dimartino, Inc. (Worcester, MA); Engineering: BR+A Consulting Engineers, Inc. (Boston); Soil Consultant: H&A of New York; Contractors: Streeter Associates (Elmira, NY), Stewart & Bennett, Inc.; Photographers: Timothy Hursley (Little Rock, AR)
    See also Writings and biographical material: Scrapbook I; Writings and biographical material: Scrapbook III.
    - Drawings, 1980-1981; working drawings (Tube 45)
    - Drawings, 1980-1981; working drawings (Tube 46)
    - Drawings, 1980; working drawings (Tube 47)
    - Drawings, 1980-1981; preliminary working drawings, working drawing sheets, detail sheets, mechanical and electrical drawings (Tube 48)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 49)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 50)
    - Drawings, 1981; drawings for publication, diagrams, shop drawings (Tube 51)
    - Drawings, 1980-1981; presentation drawings and sketches (Tube 52)
    - Presentation board 36, color photo of exterior/street
    - Presentation board 37, working details
    - Presentation board 38, color photos of exterior and interior details
    - Presentation board 39, working details
    - Presentation board 40, section (on trace)
    - Presentation board 41, section (on trace)
    - Presentation board 42, plan (on trace)
    - Presentation board 43, photo of model, sections, elevations
    - Presentation board 44, plans, sections (on trace)
    - Presentation board 45, axonometric
    - Presentation board 46, elevation
    - Project material, 1980-1981; site plans, elevations, axonometrics, model, exterior and interior, construction; sketch (Box 44)
      See also Writings and biographical material: Miscellaneous.
    - Project material, 1964-1984; reports, specifications, brochure, clippings, articles, financial, correspondence (Box 44A)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, title (dated 1981) and project synopsis, maps, analytical and explanatory diagrams, axonometrics, elevations, sections, plans, construction, models, earlier existing structures, facade, interior views, referential images; 100 (Box S-2)
  - ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - GENERAL* (ITHOE, ITHOM) Ithaca, New York [Residential]
    (Alternate names: Elm-Maple Housing, Maple Hill Apartments, West Village)
    This project consisted of three hundred and eighty-seven units of low and middle income housing. Sponsor/client: NYS Urban Development Corporation. Collaborators/partners: Mechanical: Galson & Galson Consulting Engineers, Inc. (East Syracuse); Structural: Severud, Perrone, Sturm, Conlin & Bandel (NYC); Consultant: Dr. Donald P. Greenburg; Landscape: Harold E. Schumm & Associates; Other: Sectional Structures, Inc.
    - Drawings, 1956-1971; maps, site drawings, survey, street and block layouts (Tube 53)
    - Drawings, 1969; first sketches and studies (Tube 54)
    - Drawings, 1969-1970; design development drawings (Tube 55)
    - Drawings, 1969-1970; preliminary working drawings, interior elevations (Tube 56)
    - Drawings, 1970-1972; working drawings; "as-built" drawings (Tube 57)
    - Drawings, 1970; working drawings (Tube 58)
    - Drawings, 1970; working drawings (Tube 78)
    - Project material, 1971-1989; articles, clippings, promotional and exhibition materials (Box 47A)
    - Project material, 1969-1971; plan digest, question and answer booklet, UDC reports (Box 47B)
    - Project material, 1970; specifications (text and microfilm) with handwritten notes (Box 47C)
  - ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - ELM ST. (ITHOE) 150 West Village Place Ithaca, New York (1973) [Residential]
    (Alternate names: Elm-Maple Housing, West Village Apartments)
    This project consisted of three hundred units of low and middle income housing. Sponsor/client: NYS Urban Development Corporation. Collaborators/partners: Photographers: Nathaniel Lieberman (NYC), LYONFOTO (Binghamton); C. Hadley Smith (Ithaca).
    - Drawings, 1969-1970; schematic design drawings, site work, landscaping (Tube 59)
    - Drawings, 1970-1972; working drawings, details, studies (Tube 60)
    - Drawings, 1971-1972; construction drawings for atrium and G&H units, final working drawings of atrium units (Tube 61)
    - Drawings, 1970; mid-rise working drawings, G&H units, atrium units (Tube 62)
    - Drawings, 1970-1973; "as-built" drawings (Tube 63)
    - Drawings, 1970-1973; "as-built" drawings (Tube 64)
    - Drawings, 1970-1971; mechanical and electrical drawings (including final mechanical) (Tube 65)
    - Drawings, 1970-1971; structural and shop drawings (Tube 66)
    - Drawings, 1969; preliminary and first presentation drawings (Tube 67)
    - Drawings, 1969-1971; presentation drawings (Tube 68)
    - Presentation board 47, perspective, working details, axonometric
    - Presentation board 48, perspective, elevation
    - Presentation board 49, photos of exterior and interior
    - Presentation board 50, site plan
    - Presentation board 51, photos of exterior
    - Presentation board 52, photo of model
    - Presentation board 53, photo of model, unit plans
    - Presentation board 54, site plan
    - Presentation board 55, Atrium unit plan, section "ROO."
    - Presentation board 56, section, plans of lower and upper floor
    - Project material, 1970-1973; exterior and interior of building, model, and construction; text (Box 45)
    - Project material, 1969; site plan, elevations, sections, axonometrics, working details, plans, construction (Box 46)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1970) and program description, site plans, axonometrics, elevations, sections, plans, earlier existing structures, construction, general (aerial, atrium units, midrise bldg) and interior (atrium units) views; 390 (Box S-3)
  - ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - MAPLE AVE. (ITHOM) Maple Avenue, Ithaca, New York (1973) [Residential]
    (Alternate names: Maple Hill Apartments, Elm-Maple Housing)
    This project consisted of eighty-seven units of low and middle income housing. Sponsor/client: NYS Urban Development Corporation. Collaborators/partners: Photographer: C. Hadley Smith (Ithaca).
    See also Writings and biographical material: Scrapbook III.
    - Drawings, 1969; schematic design drawings (Tube 69)
    - Drawings, 1970; working drawings (Tube 70)
    - Drawings, 1970; working drawings (Tube 71)
    - Drawings, 1970; working drawings (Tube 72)
    - Drawings, 1970-1971; structural and mechanical drawings (Tube 73)
    - Drawings, 1970; mechanical and electrical drawings (Tube 74)
    - Drawings, 1970; structural drawings (Tube 75)
    - Drawings, 1970-1971; construction drawings (Tube 76)
    - Drawings, 1969-1971; site work and landscaping (Tube 77)
    - Presentation board 57, photo of model
    - Project material, 1969; site plans, elevations, model, construction, and exterior (Box 47)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1970), site plans, elevations, models, construction, general views; 80 (Box S-3)
  - JEFFERSON SCHOOL RENOVATION AND LIBRARY MEDIA CENTER 151 Helen St., Binghamton, New York (1973) [Educational]
    (Alternate names: Thomas Jefferson Elementary School)
    Interior remodeling to school, library. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Board of Education. Collaborators/partners: Architect: Eugene Beautz
    - Drawings, 1973; working drawings (Tube 79)
  - JOHN J. ASH COMMUNITY CENTER, See NORTH BARRY STREET COMMUNITY BUILDING Olean, New York.
  - KANSAI-KAN OF THE NATIONAL DIET LIBRARY DESIGN, COMPETITION Tokyo, Japan (1996) (not built) [Government]
    Unentered competition. Sponsor/client: Ministry of Construction, Japan.
    - Project materials, 1996 (Box 82)
  - KEIFER RESIDENCE REMODELING (KRR) Ithaca, New York (not built) [Residential], for Mr. and Mrs. Jack Keifer
    - Drawings, 1965; working drawings (Tube 80)
  - LACHMAN RESIDENCE, Binghamton, New York (not built) [Residential]
    - Drawings, 1962; preliminary working drawings, studies, plans, elevations (Tube 81)
    - Project material, undated; plan, model (Box 95, Folder 21)
    - Project material, undated; Plans, section, elevations on original presentation boards [Newspaper box] (Box 90)
    - Slides, plans, models; 25 (Box S-3)
  - LAKE GEORGE WATERFRONT (LaGeo) Lake George, New York (not built) [Recreational], urban design proposal
    - Drawings, 1962-1964; base drawings, studies, working drawings (Tube 82)
    - Project material, undated; site plans (Box 92)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1964), site plans, models; 15 (Box S-3)
  - LAKE SHORE DEVELOPMENT, COMPETITION* Lausanne-Ouchy, Switzerland (undated) (not built) [Government]
    First prize entry in a competition in Switzerland for redevelopment of shore area.
    - Slides, model; 9 (Box S-3)
  - LEON RESIDENCE REMODELING, Cortland, New York (not built) [Residential], interior remodeling
    - Drawings, 1972; studies and working drawings (Tube 83)
  - MAPLE HILL APARTMENTS, See ITHACA SCATTERED SITE HOUSING - MAPLE AVE. Ithaca, New York.
  - MARLBOROUGH (MA) ELDERLY HOUSING, COMPETITION Marlborough, Massachusetts (1975) (not built) [Residential]
    Competition to build housing for the elderly and handicapped. Sponsor/client: Marlborough Housing Authority and Massachusetts Department of Community Affairs. Collaborators/partners: Associated Architect: Bruce Coleman
    - Drawings, 1975; base documents, sketches, presentation drawings (Tube 84)
    - Project material, 1975; site plans, sections, elevations, plans; correspondence; competition materials (Box 65)
    - Slides, site plans, sections, plans, models; 10 (Box S-3)
  - MARTIN'S WAY (HAMILTON COLLEGE), COMPETITION Hamilton, New York (1988) (not built) [Educational]
    Invited competition for outdoor walkway area. Sponsor/client: Hamilton College.
    - Drawings, undated; presentation drawings, sketches (Tube 85)
    - Project material, 1988; site photos, correspondence, project description (Box 95, Folder 74)
    - Slides, title slide, site plans, perspectives, sections, plans, earlier existing structures; 55 (Box S-3)
  - MCNEIL BUILDING ALTERATIONS, Cortland, New York (not built) [Commercial], interior remodeling
    - Drawings, 1979-1980; sketches and working drawings (Tube 86)
  - MELZER RESIDENCE Fayetteville, New York (1956) [Residential]
    - Project material, 1956; elevation, working details (Box 95, Folder 41)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, working details, general and interior views; 30 (Box S-3)
  - MEMORIAL BRIDGE, Binghamton, New York (undated) [Government]
    Project for redesign of bridge railing. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA).
    - Drawings, undated; section, elevation, working details (Tube 87)
    - Project material, undated; section, elevation (Box 22)
    - Slides, elevations, sections; 5 (Box S-3)
  - MENANDS HOUSING Menands, New York (not built) [Residential]
    Project consisted of three hundred units of low and middle income housing for the New York State Urban Development Corporation. Sponsor/client: NYS Urban Development Corporation. Collaborators/partners: Other: Sectional Structures, Inc.
    - Drawings, undated; studies (Tube 88)
    - Drawings, undated; presentation drawings (Tube 89)
    - Project material, 1972; site plans, sections, axonometrics, site map; report; project description (Box 50)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1971), site plans, sections, plans, working details, model, earlier existing structures; 35 (Box S-3)
  - MIAMI UNIVERSITY CHARETTE* Oxford, Ohio (not built) [Educational], downtown commercial site
    - Slides, plans, models, views of buildings, elevations, sections (dated 10/82); 30 (Box S-3)
  - MILLER SUMMER RESIDENCE (MSR) East Lake Road, Skaneateles, New York (1964) [Residential], addition to house
    (Alternate names: later known as the Biddle Residence)
    - Drawings, 1963-1964; studio proposal, working drawings (Tube 90)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 91)
    - Presentation board 59, plan, elevation, sections (color), dated 1955
    - Project material, 1963-1964; snapshots of model and construction (Box 57)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94A)
    - Slides, plans, working details, model, construction and reconstruction, facade, side, back and interior view, exterior and interior details; 110 (Box S-3)
  - MONDEV PROJECT, Binghamton, New York (not built) [Government]
    Urban design coordination of proposal by Mondev (Montreal Development Company, Ltd.). Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA).
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1970), site plans, sections, perspectives; 20 (Box S-3)
  - MONROEVILLE AREA CIVIC CENTER, COMPETITION Monroeville, Pennsylvania (1982) (not built) [Cultural]
    Competition for civic center (not submitted). Sponsor/client: Intergovernmental Advisory Board (made up of the Municipality of Monroeville and the Gateway School District).
    - Drawings, undated; base and site maps, elevations, sections (Tube 92)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 93)
    - Project material, 1982; site plans, elevations, sections, site; correspondence; competition materials (Box 66)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1982), site plans, perspectives, sections, plans, earlier existing; 25 (Box S-3)
  - NATIONAL MUSEUM OF KOREA, COMPETITION Seoul, Korea (1995) (not built) [Cultural]
    Major international competition for museum building. Sponsor/client: Ministry of Culture and Sports, Republic of Korea. Collaborators/partners: Associated Architects: Bruce Abbey, Joel Bostick, Mark Shapiro.
    - Drawings, undated; base maps, presentation drawings (Tube 94)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 95)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 96)
    - Project material, 1994-1995; site plan, sections, elevations, isometrics, plans; competition materials; catalog of entries (Box 9)
  - NORDWESTSTADT, COMPETITION Frankfurt, Germany (undated) (not built) [Residential], housing competition